<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>Sanjeet's Blogposts</title>
	<id>https://spacesanjeet.me/</id>
	<link rel="alternate" href="https://spacesanjeet.me/"/>
	<link rel="self" href="https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/feed.xml"/>
	<updated>2025-06-21T15:27:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>Sanjeet Patel</name>
	</author>
	<entry>
	  <title>Levels of Accountability</title>
	  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2025-03-31-levels-of-accountability.html"/>
	  <id>https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2025-03-31-levels-of-accountability.html</id>
	  <published>2025-03-31T15:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2025-03-31T15:00:00Z</updated>
	  <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/levels-of-accountability.png&quot; alt=&quot;A stacked venn diagram of individual, community, and government.&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			A stacked venn diagram representing the overlapping relationships between the individual, community, and government.
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I was doom scrolling on Instagram one day when it hit me that there may me levels to how people take accountability to a problem in society. And this may be universal. Here is an example: The Ganges is the single most sacred river in the world and hosts the largest gathering of humanity once every 12 years.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					It is also one of the most polluted bodies of water in the world. I have seen countless videos of foreigners trolling and hammering Indians seeing the river this polluted. Now I have seen different opinions for the reason the Ganges is polluted to such a horrible extent.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;
						Level 1. Individual. Pollution stems from individuals and their disregard towards mutually accepted societal norms.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;
						Level 2. Community. Pollution stems from the failure of the community to keep a river clean which is sacred to them.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;
						Level 3. Government. Pollution stems from the utter mismanagement and ignorance of the state towards keeping the river clean.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I believe based on how things are portrayed in the media, people tend to hover between different levels of accountability. However, in practically every large-scale issue in this country, I have seen people skip the first two and bell the 3rd level instead. Why is that? Why do people tend to ignore individual and community level accountability and blame the government for the ills in society?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Individuals make a community, and multiple communities together make a government. Indian political system is highly decentralized with elections and governments all the way down to single village units. And this is where another question arises. If people tend to ignore their individual and group accountability and rest the liability on the government, which level of government are they referring to? Is it their local rural/city government such as village panchayats and municipal corporations, is it the district level authorities, is it the state government, or is it the central government?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I do not believe in the concept of a top-down solution in a country’s political and social system. You cannot expect a minister sitting in his air-conditioned office in Delhi to understand why different regions around Ganges have different levels of pollution, some worse than others. That’s the responsibility of the local municipalities to find and report.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					What people in this country fail to realize is that central government (synonymous with a single word Modi since 2014) plans and creates policies. They do not have the power to directly implement their directives at the ground level. That is the job of the state and local governments. That is precisely why we have a Union, State, and the Concurrent list. In our example of the Ganges, the water bodies and public health come under the purview of the state governments.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					My understanding is that India has long been a mixed economy, but socialist roots have always had a strong hold. This is exactly the reason why many Indians hate the idea of privatization and blame Modi for the recent shift towards aggressive capitalism. What they fail to realize is that the LPG (liberalization, privatization, and globalization) policy was adopted way back in 1991. Modi was not even a remote part of the government system back then.&lt;/p&gt;			 
				&lt;p&gt;
					The strong socialist roots lead people to blame the government for any minute inconvenience. Indians do not have the concept of individual and community level accountability. This is why things never get done in India without some form of government and political intervention. For example, we Indians expect the government to take care of even the community parks. People in India believe in the top-down approach which is a horrible way to solve ground issues and for community driven development.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Different levels of government have a major role in shaping individual opinion and accountability but ultimately the onus is on the people of the community themselves to find their way out of issues which have long plagued them. For example, while the Bihar state government can implement stronger education and literary policies, it will be useless unless the people in the society can utilize them to the fullest and change their fortunes.&lt;/p&gt;			 
				&lt;p&gt;
					This is my understanding, but I do not know how people in more developed countries hold themselves accountable for the things that happen in society or them too hover on the 3rd level instead. I guess most people at least try at some point to introspect but since at the individual level humans are incapable of making large scale impact, they default back to how they perceive and who they blame the societal rot for.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Another recent example: the Tesla takedown movement. Individuals around the world, but mostly in the USA and Europe, have this understanding that they can peacefully and non-violently protest against a non-elected billionaire meddling in the affairs of the state. They can stop purchasing Tesla vehicles and more widely stop engaging with all companies the person in attention operates.&lt;/p&gt;			 
				&lt;p&gt;
					And thus, while the majority of the population may still believe that the state is at fault for allowing this to happen, individuals and communities realize that they have the power in their hands to trigger change. I wonder how many of those Tesla takedown protestors are voters who thought they were doing the right thing when they helped elect the current head of the state. But if they are on the streets voicing their protest, they have formally utilized level 1 and 2 of the ladders which lead to societal change. Because let’s be honest, the government doesn’t usually give a shit. They need to be compelled to do stuff.&lt;/p&gt; 
				&lt;p&gt;
					And that is why I believe the levels work. Side-stepping or jumping up the levels will just leave the issues to rot the system and hinder progress. Indians need to start owning the issues. We elected the government. We set the agenda. Not vice versa. So, we should own accountability first. Once we start doing it en masse, there’s no going back.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>40 Minutes</title>
	  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2025-02-09-40-minutes.html"/>
	  <id>https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2025-02-09-40-minutes.html</id>
	  <published>2025-02-09T15:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2025-02-09T15:00:00Z</updated>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
					During my visit to an exam center a week ago, an event left me thinking about my life and things I take for granted.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					While waiting for the bus at the stop, I saw a man sitting a few feet away from me, waiting uneasily. I didn’t notice it at first, but when I forced myself to take a serious look, I was left numb. He was a blind man. He must be in his late 30s. Before I came to the bus stop, he had somehow recruited two small kids who I am guessing study at the school behind the stop.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The kids were on the lookout to stop any incoming buses for the man. Below is everything that happened to the best of my memory.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bus-stop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Interior of contemporary public transport on sunny day&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			Interior of contemporary public transport on sunny day; Image Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pexels.com/photo/interior-of-contemporary-public-transport-on-sunny-day-3802736/&quot;&gt;Pexels&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;hr&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The man: “What is this lying here on the side?”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The kids: “They are clothes. Somebody’s clothes.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“Oh, these are clothes.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“Yes, they are.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“Is a bus coming?”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“No, not yet. We are watching, sit tight.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“Is this a new bus stop they have constructed?”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“Yes, this a new bus stop.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“This one is so much better than the one on the other side of the road.” (There’s no bus stop on the other side of the road, people have to wait standing on the sides.)&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“A bus is coming.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The man stands up and walks a little ahead in anticipation of the arrival of a bus.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“It’s coming?”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“No, it’s still a little far away. You sit down, we will call out when it arrives.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The man walks back, and gently takes the seat again, still uneasy waiting for the bus.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					A blue color local bus arrived but it was filled to the brim. The kids intelligently recognized that the man would not be able to find a comfortable seat on this one and they couldn’t trust a local bus to drop the man safely to his destination. The man recognizes that a bus has arrived and stands up and walks to the edge of the stop waiting for the kids to help him board it.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“The bus has come?”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“It’s the blue one. Not the red.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“So it’s a blue one.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The man walks back and takes the seat again.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The kids move back and forth from side to side, looking for a bus. And they spot one. This time a red colored bus licensed by the state with a defined route.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					“A red bus is coming.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The man stands up confidently this time and walks to the edge of the stop. The bus had seats available and I boarded it. The kids, walk over to the front of the bus to ask the driver if the bus will go to the stop the man wants to go. They run back and ask the conductor of the bus to help the man board the bus and drop him at the destination. He helps the man board the bus and the kids move back as the bus starts moving. The man is unsure where the empty seats are and stands in the middle perhaps hoping somebody would direct him. The conductor helps him sit beside me on the right side of the bus.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					After a few minutes, the conductor walks over and asks me for the ticket. I tell him my destination and give him the cash. He gives back the change with my ticket. However, he then moves forward without asking the man for his ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					My stop arrived in about 15 minutes. Before the bus stopped, I stood up and gently asked the man to provide me some leg space so I could move out (I was in the window seat). He complied and after a small struggle asking people to move out of the way to the door, I deboarded the bus.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					From there, I took an electric rickshaw to my center, took my exam, and went back home. Back to normality.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;hr&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I don’t know the specific reason why I can’t forget about this particular set of events on a pretty normal day. The moment I got off the bus, I wanted to write about it. Put my thoughts into words. Why does it seem to impact me much?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					After that first serious look at the man, I could only gather enough willpower to look at him directly one more time while he was beside me on the bus. His eyes were shut and I couldn’t seem to determine if the eyelids were sewn together or if the man had a completely different set of eyelids I had never seen before.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The man never once made me uncomfortable. There’s no reason. But I felt an immense feeling of guilt take over me for the entire journey.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Why did I never once try to talk to him?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Why did I simply walk past him and board the bus when I knew he was going in the same direction?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					How confident was I in the abilities of the kids he had somehow recruited?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Perhaps I was taken over by whatever I was looking at and wanted it to unfold without interfering.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I instantly thanked god for having enough grace and mercy that I have eyesight with which I can not only enjoy the existence of the living but also aid me in fulfilling the menial tasks I take for granted. I cannot fathom the level of struggle the man has to go through daily just to get himself in a position where he fully feels safe and confident that he has done things right.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I don’t know the names or the grades of the kids who helped the man. But those kids are exactly the kind we need more. Empathetic and determined. Intelligent in their actions. The bus conductor who helped the man on the bus doesn’t earn much. Probably just enough to feed his family. Yet he never asked for the ticket. He knew what he had to do and went by it. Empathetic and intelligent.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I wonder how often when people like me come into contact with the handicapped, they drop their usual attitude and try to be nice and helpful. It was beautiful to see. I have never said ‘god bless’ more times than I did in those 40 mins. I hope the man got off where he wanted to and reached his destination safely.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Maybe if we all start to be more empathetic towards one another, we can get meaningful things done and create a better society where everybody feels safe. Next time something like this happens, rather than going numb, I will try to be steadfast in what I am supposed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Lesson learned.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Tennis in 2024</title>
	  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2024-12-26-tennis-in-2024.html"/>
	  <id>https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2024-12-26-tennis-in-2024.html</id>
	  <published>2024-12-26T15:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2024-12-26T15:00:00Z</updated>
	  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
					A lot happened on the ATP Tour during the 2024 season. Tennis has seen an eventful year, from players winning their first titles to a pair cementing their control over the slams to legends bidding farewell to the sport. What I am however particularly interested in and going to talk about will be based on these players:&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;ol style=&quot;columns: 3&quot;&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Alexander Zverev&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;Daniil Medvedev&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;Novak Djokovic&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;The Big-2 (aka Jannik Sinner and Carlos Alcaraz)&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;Predictions for 2025&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ol&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Yes, in that particular order. I have some interesting thoughts about this group of players and how they have played and panned out over 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;
					Alexander Zverev&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Zverev has dumped that easy-going tennis personality around himself. He seems more intent, active, and focused than ever on trying to win the final silverware that has remained out of his grasp: a grand slam title.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					He has won ATP 250s, 500s, and Masters 1000s, and is an Olympic champion. He has played 2 grand slam finals. Worthy of being one of the great players of the modern era. I don’t think he wants to appear in the history books like that. And it is correct of him to think so. For somebody like Zverev who has so few holes in his game and is locked in most of the time, a grand slam title would be a fitting achievement.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The problem is, that Zverev has always had to battle the big boys deep into the slams. But nobody promised him that he would not face the top 5 and top 10s at slams. However much of his failures deep into slams can be attributed to his attitude. And I don’t mean he has a negative attitude.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/zverev-fo24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Zverev in the post-final ceremony at the Roland Garros&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			Zverev in the post-final ceremony at the Roland Garros; Image Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/rolandgarros/status/1799898260103958780/photo/1&quot;&gt;Roland Garros/X&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Take for example: the US Open Semifinal in 2021. Djokovic tied with Zverev 4-6, 6-2, 6-4, 4-6. The latter being the younger contender, the fresher, and showing intent during the 4th set. Having a realistic chance to topple Djokovic’s hopes of a calendar slam and enter the final.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The deciding set read: 6-2 Djokovic. It was a horrible display of mental fortitude against somebody like Djokovic who was more gassed than Zverev at that point in time. Zverev failed to capitalize on the opportunity and failed under the pressure to convert the “chance” he believed he had. (Djokovic ultimately was gassed enough after going 5 sets against Zverev that he lost 0-3 to Medvedev in the final.)&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Another example: Zverev vs Carlos Alcaraz, Roland Garros 2024. Zverev led everyone’s favorite 3-6, 6-2, 7-5. Alcaraz was the fan and expert’s pick to win but if there was one guy in the whole draw who could take out Alcaraz, it was Zverev. And he seemed to realize it. That he had a “chance.”&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Leading Alcaraz 2-1 in the final would give him enough leeway to slow the match down and take the chances as they come without taking risks.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The final two sets: 1-6, 2-6. It was a disaster. Absolutely no fight at all. Alcaraz was able to find the gap in Zverev’s baseline just enough to force winners and catch him mentally lacking. Zverev was tuned out of the match, not able to find his pinpoint serves and forcing Alcaraz to commit errors he had done quite comfortably for the previous 2 sets. Going up 2-1 against the favorite meant, he had a “chance,” and he buckled under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					One more recent example that doesn’t need any more explaining because as you may guess, ended in the same fashion. Daniil Medvedev vs Zverev, Australian Open Semifinal 2024: 5–7, 3–6, 7–6, 7–6, 6–3.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Zverev consistently clocked great results on the Tour in 2024: won 2 ATP Masters 1000 titles (Rome and Paris) and went deep at multiple slams: a semifinal and a final at AO and Roland Garros respectively and R16 at Wimbledon and a quarterfinal at US Open (defeated by Taylor Fritz in both instances who has become famous for being “Zverev’s kryptonite”; Fritz leads their H2H 7-5, with 4 of those wins coming in 2024 alone) and a semifinal at the year ending Nitto ATP Finals where he lost to, yes you guessed it right, Taylor Fritz.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/zverev-fritz-h2h.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Zverev vs Fritz H2H&quot;&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/zverev-fritz-h2h-matches.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Zverev vs Fritz H2H&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			Image Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atptour.com/en/players/atp-head-2-head/alexander-zverev-vs-taylor-fritz/z355/fb98&quot;&gt;ATP&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Zverev is 27 years old and is evidently at his peak physical capabilities. Not being able to crack the moment and assert dominance at slams would now mean that he will be closer with every passing grand slam loss to going down in the history books without a slam.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					2025 should be the year Alexander Zverev rises to his peak potential and captures a slam. Yes Jannik Sinner and Carlos Alcaraz are all over the tour right now and Taylor Fritz seems to have found a way to pocket him every time they play but if somebody told me that Zverev is any less a player than those mentioned above, you can be sure that I would laugh. He is in the same league as Sinner and Alcaraz. It may sound cocky, but that is the truth.&lt;p&gt; 
				&lt;p&gt;
					2025: Alexander Zverev. I am watching.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;
					Daniil Medvedev&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Daniil Medvedev is the player I wanted Zverev to transition to. In terms of success at the grand slams that is to say. But 2024 was the worst year for Medvedev in terms of success on the tour for as long as I have seen him play. What started as a promising year ended in a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Medvedev began the year on a strong note by playing the final at the Australian Open 2024. However, it was painful to see him lose out on a grand slam victory in Australia to Sinner in the same fashion to which he lost to Rafael Nadal in 2022. This year however it was certain that Medvedev was not the favorite to win the final in Melbourne.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					To see him go 2 sets to love up against Sinner, however, was a surprise that wasn’t on my bingo card for that match. Ultimately though, playing 2 consecutive 5-setters on the way to the finals against quality players such as Zverev (in the semifinal where Medvedev came back from 2 sets down) and Hubi Hurkacz meant that he was out of gas by the end of 2nd set and Sinner started to toy with Medvedev’s baseline tennis to assert dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Medvedev went on to play just 1 additional final all year at the Indian Wells Masters 1000 where he lost to Carlos Alcaraz. Apart from these finals, Medvedev had a horror show. He played a few semifinals and looked to be back in form at places but ultimately was not able to crack his opponents deep into the tournaments this year. Alcaraz in particular was too big an opponent for Medvedev to solve and lost to him 3 times this year, 2 semifinals and a final. Thus his bad run of form against Sinner and Alcaraz which started back in March 2023 continued this year.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/medvedev-ao24.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Daniil Medvedev in the post-final ceremony at AO 2024&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			Daniil Medvedev in the post-final ceremony at AO 2024; Image Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/C2rWzCKozqB/&quot;&gt;Daniil Medvedev/Instagram&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I have a theory for the lack of results for Medvedev on the tour since the turn of 2024. Daniil is a baseliner who feels comfortable standing deep in his return position and with long rallies. Over the years he has choked his opponents with extensive baselining that is tiring to witness, let alone play. At the peak of his form, Medvedev regularly baited his opponents into submission by dragging them into long rallies which usually ended up with unforced errors or winners in the open court.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					For long, he relied on his baseline tennis for results. However come 2023 and with the rise of aggressive baseliners such as Jannik Sinner and Carlos Alcaraz, Medvedev has had to endure a tough period of extensive failures against the two. One of the generally accepted reasons for his lack of wins against the two mentioned players is Medvedev’s over-reliance on his serve and baseline tennis. Over time and with age, baselining for a consistent duration of time has created physical dents in his tennis. Medvedev is 28 years old and cannot rely on his baseline tennis to overpower opponents with an increasingly aggressive style of play.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Another reason is his deep return positions. Alcaraz initially and now several players on tour have started to use this play by Medvedev to their advantage by bailing themselves out of long rallies through drop shots; and since Medvedev’s deep return position usually translates to deep baseline tennis, he often chokes on trying to return drop shots.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					One adjustment Medvedev made in his tennis was to come closer to the baseline to return serves, but also effectively utilizing drop shots and aggressive serve-volley and plus-one shot combinations in his own game. This combo was the reason for his quick 2-0 lead against Jannik Sinner in the AO 2024 final. But was the adjustment made due to the style of his opponent or due to his fatigue, we will never know. I side with the latter because coming into the finals, it was certain that Sinner was the younger and fresher of the two, and recent results all but suggested the Italian’s victory.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					To see Medvedev utilize serve volleys and be aggressive in rallies and often being the first one to come up to the net was a pleasant surprise but one that also positively helped his game. However, the lack of consistency in utilizing these changes and implementing other variations in his game meant that not just the best players in the world, but more players outside the top 10 and 20 started to significantly hurt Medvedev this year.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The poor run of results from Medvedev has meant that since May 2023 when he last won an ATP Tour title at the Rome Masters 1000, he has played 5 finals and lost all of them; 3 finals to Sinner, one a piece to Djokovic and Alcaraz. For Medvedev to change his fortunes, he has to find solutions to tackle the best players in the world and bring variations in his game which can help him regain his form and challenge for grand slam titles once again.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					2025: Daniil Medvedev. I am watching.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;
					Novak Djokovic&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					If somebody told Novak Djokovic at the beginning of the year that he would not win any grand slam titles, not win any Masters 1000 titles, and would not win any title all year but the Olympic gold medal, he would have taken the deal. Makes total sense.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Djokovic is a 3-time career-slam holder, is the only player in history to win every Masters 1000 title 2 or more times, has the most no. of slams and Masters 1000 titles, most weeks at World no. 1, and has an endless list of other achievements in his resume. What he didn’t have at the turn of 2024 was: an Olympic gold medal.&lt;/p&gt; 
				&lt;p&gt;
					He won it this year and won after defeating en route not only his greatest rival ever, but also by defeating massive favorite Carlos Alcaraz in straight sets in the final, to whom he had lost a 2nd consecutive Wimbledon final a month ago in straight sets.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/djokovic-oly24.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Djokovic with the celebratory pose with his Olympic Gold Medal&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			Djokovic with the celebratory pose with his Olympic Gold Medal; Image Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yardbarker.com/tennis/articles/former_world_no_25_explains_why_olympic_champion_novak_djokovic_is_very_bad_for_tennis/s1_17325_40712949&quot;&gt;Yardbarker&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					It was the victory that was heard around the world. Before the 4th of August 2024, the debate for the greatest men’s player on the tour was pretty much muted due to the total sweep by Djokovic of every big tennis statistic known to mankind. One achievement though, that remained out of grasp from the great Serbian was an Olympic gold. After coming agonizingly close to completing his Olympic dream at Tokyo 2020, Djokovic was determined, relentless in his pursuit, and most of all, locked in to complete tennis once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					In what I consider to be the match of the year, Novak Djokovic with a strap on his right knee, for 2 hours and 50 minutes battled Alcaraz as if though he had not been the same man who was obliterated just a month before by the same adversary.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					After almost 3 hours on the red clay with the sun overlooking the Phillipe Chatrier, Djokovic buried Alcaraz with a ground stroke forehand winner which will go down in the history books as the shot which upgraded the status of the greatest player in tennis history to a demigod.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Watching Djokovic play after his Olympic triumph was like watching a 1980s Ford Escort on the streets, the once best-selling car which while retains its aura, is now out of gas.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					While Djokovic hunted the last of his original glory moments, he saw his old-time rivals and pals retire left and right. Dominic Thiem retired from the sport after suffering a continuous string of poor results which plagued him ever since his wrist injury in 2021. Andy Murray called on his time this year along with Rafael Nadal who played his last official tennis match for his country at the Davis Cup finals in Malaga, Spain.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					With Roger already retired and with two of the other Big-4 rivals calling their time in 2024, it remains no mystery to anybody that Djokovic will in due time, call it quits too. For all his exploits on the ATP Tour for 2 decades, there remains nothing to be won anymore that is worthy of his time and physical energy.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					At 37 years old, it is now not the question of “if” but “when” Djokovic retires. For now, though, he has paired up with Andy Murray to sit in his box and coach him at the Australian Open 2025.&lt;/p&gt; 
				&lt;p&gt;
					2025: Novak Djokovic. A long-time fan will be watching without expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;
					The Big-2 and others&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Sinner and Alcaraz split the 2024 grand slams between themselves. While Sinner became the first man in history to take out Djokovic in an Australian Open semifinal, Alcaraz defeated Djokovic for a 2nd consecutive time to clinch Wimbledon. He also won his first Roland Garros title after denying Zverev in 5 sets, while Sinner won the US Open and the Nitto ATP Finals to end the year as the world no. 1.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/sinner-ao24.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Jannik Sinner with a celebratory pose after winning Australian Open 2024&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			Jannik Sinner with a celebratory pose after winning Australian Open 2024; Image Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.optionstheedge.com/topic/people/jannik-sinner-wins-australian-open-2024-capture-first-grand-slam-title&quot;&gt;Options, The Edge&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;
					In the big tournaments in 2024 (Grand Slams + Masters 1000), Sinner and Alcaraz became routine names. In the 2010s, when the Big-3 and the Big-4 routinely featured in the semifinals and finals of all major tournaments and gate-kept all the titles for themselves, it was astonishing to witness the firepower and skill gap between them and the rest of the tour.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Something similar has started to take shape in the current setup of the tour as well. While there is no clear 3rd and 4th wheel, Sinner and Alcaraz seem to be content with making gains among themselves. And while their rivalry will entertain fans for the coming decade, the gap between them and the rest of the tour is widening at an increasing pace. Alcaraz already sits on 4 slam titles, while Sinner made big gains in 2024 winning 2 of the available 4.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/atpliveranking-25-dec24.png&quot; alt=&quot;ATP Live Ranking as of 25th December 2024&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
						Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://live-tennis.eu/en/atp-live-ranking&quot;&gt;ATP Live Ranking&lt;/a&gt;; as of 25th December 2024
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					For a pair that is relatively younger than the current top 10, Sinner 23, and Alcaraz 21, they have also started to widen the gap not just with age but with titles won as well. In the current top 10, apart from Djokovic, Sinner and Alcaraz (2+4) have more slam titles than the rest combined (Medvedev-1).&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					One can hope that the playing field will turn out to be more competitive in 2025, which looks likely considering Zverev and Fritz attained their career-high rankings this year. If both of them stop canceling each other out and focus on improving their overall game against the top 5 in the world, we can witness some interesting matches and results in the upcoming season.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Age is on the side of Sinner and Alcaraz and thus they would feel confident of continuing their run of success. Unless more of the current top-10 make headway, the pair looks clear to dominate the tour going forward. I expect more young players to make their runs into the top 10, namely Jack Draper (career-high 15) and Holger Rune (13). Among other strong contenders include Lorenzo Musetti (17), Arthur Fils (career-high 20), and Jiří Lehečka (28).&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					In brief, though, Jannik Sinner and Carlos Alcaraz look miles clear of their competition right now, and with the vacations coming to an end and the Australian Open around the corner, we may once again expect to see similar faces on the podium unless some of the aforementioned players or surprise entrants can show what gains they have made in the off-season.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;
					Predictions for the 2025 ATP Season&lt;/h2&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					This year I didn’t make any predictions for the tennis calendar. I was mostly focused on following the sport rather than writing and thus didn’t come up with my usual prediction post before the Australian Open. This time though, things are different, and thus here are my predictions for tennis calendar 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;ol&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;
						&lt;strong&gt;Novak Djokovic will win the Australian Open&lt;/strong&gt;. This prediction has more to do with my faith in the former world. No 1. He has played no tennis since early October apart from his exhibition match with Juan Martín del Potro, another legend who bid farewell to tennis after winning 6-4, 7-5 and embracing Djokovic at the net with both in tears. Djokovic thus has had an extended off-season and now with Andy Murray in his corner, I expect him to start the year with vigor to capture his 25th slam. As a counter-put, I don’t see anybody other than Sinner winning in Melbourne once again.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;
						&lt;strong&gt;Alexander Zverev will win Roland Garros or a slam title&lt;/strong&gt;. As mentioned before, 2025 should be Zverev’s hunting year after making big gains in 2024. Fully expect him to capture a slam title, preferably on the red clay at Phillipe Chatrier.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;
						&lt;strong&gt;Jannik Sinner will win Wimbledon&lt;/strong&gt;. About time he wins the biggest slam title in all of tennis. Alcaraz is a 2-time defending champion and grass seems to suit his natural game, but Sinner looks better suited to convert his hard court performances on grass.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;
						&lt;strong&gt;Taylor Fritz will win his home slam, the US Open&lt;/strong&gt;. Fritz made big gains this year attaining his career-high ranking and making final runs at the US Open and the year-ending Nitto ATP Finals. I expect Fritz to remain in contention for a slam title this year and become the first American man since Andy Roddick in 2003 to win one.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ol&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Apart from the slams, here are some of my predictions based on intuition alone.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;ol&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Daniil Medvedev to win a slam/multiple Masters 1000 titles.&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;Holger Rune to re-enter the top 10/win another Masters 1000 title/make multiple deep runs at slams.&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;Jack Draper to win a Masters 1000 title/make a deep run at a slam/enter the top 10.&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;Stefanos Tsitsipas to win a clay Masters 1000 title/go deep at Roland Garros.&lt;/li&gt;

					&lt;li&gt;Casper Ruud is to play another slam final/make a serious deep run at Wimbledon.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ol&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					It was a great year for tennis fans like me and I expect more of the same in the upcoming season. Tennis seemed to have been in a transition phase for the past 2 seasons, which now looks to have been completed. I expect more intense matches, new rivalries, and new champions.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					I wish everyone happy holidays and a happy new year.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Who then, shall motivate?</title>
	  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2024-12-19-who-then-shall-motivate.html"/>
	  <id>https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2024-12-19-who-then-shall-motivate.html</id>
	  <published>2024-12-19T15:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2024-12-19T15:00:00Z</updated>
	  <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src=&quot;../images/who-then-shall-motivate.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Pericles who was a Greek politician and general during the Golden Age of Athens is seen here delivering a speech to a gathering of men.&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			Pericles, Greek politician and general during the Golden Age of Athens; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/topics/ancient-greece/pericles&quot;&gt;Image source&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Gentlemen, what is the reason we gather here today? Why am I to stand amongst you all to deliver a meek and futile speech? Haven&#x27;t we been told enough? Or is it that you wait for one last push, either to break our enemies or break away?&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					In all of humankind gentlemen, there hasn&#x27;t been one recorded instance of a speech delivered so powerful and so mighty, that it instilled in its listeners the truth of the vanity to fight one&#x27;s enemies. Who which motivates you does not guarantee you the success you yourself dream about.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Am I to tell you now to flee? To stop chasing the truth and victory you all have so long desired for? And tell me why I should do it. To convince another human being who already has its sight set on something else is like talking down a lion once it has tasted blood in its mouth.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					And so gentlemen, what should be expected from me? You will find so many men, a great number of philosophers, and even a greater number of administrators tell you that its one&#x27;s duty to fulfill and complete the actions they have set on about to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Those who motivate men never mention failure as an option. Those men who encourage, never talk about the hurdles and failures set along the way. Those who motivate, motivate for success alone. BE READY FOR THE VICTORY. CHERISH THE MOMENT ONCE YOU GET HOLD OF THAT VICTORY.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					So tell me dear all, of hundreds and thousands of you ready to die chasing victory for the great king and your beloved, are you ready also to taste defeats and failures? Are you ready to break away when you see the failure coming your way? &lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Those who motivate you, those who encourage you, go to great lengths to describe the victories and how to win. TELL ME. DO THEY EVER READY OTHERS FOR FAILURES AND DEFEATS? NO GENTLEMEN, NO, THERE HASN&#x27;T BEEN ONE RECORDED INSTANCE IN ALL OF HUMAN HISTORY WHERE THIS HAS HAPPENED.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					You must face failure yourself. For all the motivation and the encouragement you might perceive on your path to glory, they will never once prepare you for the failures. Only you, and you alone gentlemen, ready yourself for failures. Readiness and being able to absorb and render numb the failure and the defeat comes from within oneself. No man, no philosopher, no administrator, not even me my brothers, can ready another for failure. &lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					So now you must make the decision here and now. Who am I to compel you people to break away now this deep in enemy territory? We must strive to accomplish our goals and make our enemies surrender. And unless we achieve that gentlemen, ready yourself for failure. &lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Because it is not me who can bring you the victory gentlemen, you must earn it through your own actions, and thus still, failure is yours even more.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;hr&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					No specific reason why I am writing this. I just happen to be thinking about motivation and failures today while doing household chores and decided to weave something around those words. I wonder what you guys think about this.
				&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Is it too late?</title>
	  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2024-10-14-is-it-too-late.html"/>
	  <id>https://spacesanjeet.me/blog/2024-10-14-is-it-too-late.html</id>
	  <published>2024-10-14T15:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2024-10-14T15:00:00Z</updated>
	  <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
					&lt;img src = &quot;../images/gevra.jpg&quot; alt = &quot;India&#x27;s largest coal mine, Gevra Coal Mines (SECL)&quot;&gt;
					&lt;figcaption&gt;
	    			India&#x27;s largest coal mine, Gevra Coal Mines (SECL) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-06-08/plan-for-one-of-world-s-biggest-coal-mines-challenged-in-india&quot;&gt;Image source&lt;/a&gt;
	  				&lt;/figcaption&gt;
				&lt;/figure&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					We had this engaging and thoughtful discussion at my college on sustainable development and how can brands define their objectives to achieve their sustainable missions.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					During the lecture, several points were raised by the professor and some of my peers. Some of them become the talking points of today’s post due to their perceived significance to me.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					One of the starting points of the discussion was related to climate change and if it is real. One of my peers quoted that Vivek Ganapathy Ramaswamy, one of the candidates in the Republican Presidential Primary, said on national television that climate change is a hoax.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;lite-youtube videoid=&quot;Ye9lg8hWfQg&quot;&gt;&lt;/lite-youtube&gt;
				&lt;hr&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					My professor replied by saying that various politicians and head of the states of many countries around the world have hesitated to accept the changing of the climate and its implications on the world due its affects on economy and GDP growth.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					&lt;strong&gt;But first, what is actually climate change?&lt;/strong&gt;
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;blockquote&gt;
	  				&lt;p&gt;“Climate change refers to long-term shifts in temperatures and weather patterns. Such shifts can be natural, due to changes in the sun’s activity or large volcanic eruptions. But since the 1800s, human activities have been the main driver of climate change, primarily due to the burning of fossil fuels like coal, oil and gas.”&lt;/p&gt;
	  				&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/climatechange/what-is-climate-change&quot;&gt; United Nations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	    		&lt;p&gt;
					One of the examples quoted by the professor focused on how if the head of the state of India openly accepted that climate change is real and needs to be dealt with utmost urgency; it will lead to the complete overhaul of the government’s internal and external policies as well as any and all new projects taking place in the country.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The government will have to abide by the acceptance of the head of the state and will have to focus and work towards reducing and rejecting projects that have short as well as long term climate and environmental impact.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					All subsidies and grants available to various upcoming MSME’s and startups would be under scrutiny and only be approved once it is ascertained that the operations of these firms will not lead to any adverse environmental impacts.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					As one of the fastest growing countries in the world with on pace to become a developed nation by 2047, India cannot afford to lose sight of its goals in trying to accommodate climate and environmental care.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					GDP growth is an important determinant of the development of economies such as India and thus trying to heavily enforce climate goals can hamper and slow down the economic growth.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;aside&gt;				
					&lt;p&gt;Coal is one of the most abundant fossil fuels in India. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coal.nic.in/en/major-statistics/coal-indian-energy-choice&quot;&gt; Ministry of Coal&lt;/a&gt;, about 55% of the total energy needs of the country are met with coal alone.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;/aside&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					India has started to diversify its energy needs with solar energy taking a central stage in it’s move to renewable energy. But it is without a doubt that one of the fastest growing countries on the planet continues to rely on coal as the driver of its economic health.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					One of the terms used by the professor to address the hesitation by people and politicians to accept climate change is: &lt;strong&gt;climate skepticism&lt;/strong&gt;.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;blockquote&gt;
					&lt;p&gt;“A climate skeptic is someone who does not believe that changes in the earth’s climate risk environmental catastrophe.”&lt;/p&gt;
	    			&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/climate-sceptic&quot;&gt; Collins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	    		&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	    		&lt;p&gt;
					I think a lot of people in the world are either climate skeptic or deniers. It will be wrong to put people who are ignorant about climate change under climate skeptics but it won’t change too much even if we do that.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					We have deserts recording excess rains for a continued period of time and scenes of floods and deluge.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Sahara desert, the largest and one of the most driest places in the world received its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/energy-and-environment/sahara-desert-witnesses-first-floods-in-50-years/article68745136.ece&quot;&gt; first floods in about 50 years this week&lt;/a&gt;. The Moroccan government reported that just 2 days worth of rains have exceeded the yearly average of rainfall that many of the country’s region receive.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;lite-youtube videoid=&quot;xmiua1GWWPc&quot;&gt;&lt;/lite-youtube&gt;
				&lt;hr&gt;
				&lt;blockquote&gt;
	    			&lt;p&gt;“It’s been 30 to 50 years since we’ve had this much rain in such a short space of time.”&lt;/p&gt;
	    			&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;– Houssine Youabeb of Morocco’s General Directorate of Meteorology&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	    		&lt;/blockquote&gt;
	    		&lt;p&gt;
					Thar desert, located in the west of India have on record exceeded normal rainfall levels for over 20 years now. The region &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/for-20-years-thar-getting-more-rain-than-normal/articleshow/114199152.cms&quot;&gt; was 1 out of 36 subdivisions that have received excess rainfall this year&lt;/a&gt; but it was hardly a surprise as the trend has been seen in rainfall over the region in recent years. This undeniably tells us about the indications of the shifting monsoon patterns in a warming world.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;strong&gt;The deserts are getting wet and the plains drier&lt;/strong&gt;, my professor exclaimed during the lecture.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					Which leads us to the question, is it too late? Is is too late to undo the climate change which humans have caused to the planet? I don’t have an answer to this question. Neither does my professor.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					One of my peers questioned the professor that why is it expected that we do not throw the plastic bottles into the waters when the manufacturers of these bottles dump their waste in the same waters? Isn’t it hypocrisy to call out individuals rather than just reigning in on these corporations that continue to damage the environment and contribute to the climate change.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					The professor said that one simple solution to the problem is to simply stop consuming what we deem is harmful to the planet. The peer responded by saying that how is it possible to stop consumption and why can’t the government simply reign in on the corporations who are responsible for the environmental damage to begin with.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					My professor was quick to add that while it may be tough to stop consumption of products that we deem harmful to the planet, it is one of the easiest and effective ways to contribute towards environmental safeguarding. Eliminating the demand that incentivizes the producers to manufacture the goods that harm the environment is indeed an easy way out through this, albeit in a slow and long term process.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					But the truth is unknown. Maybe it is in the front of us. But we do not know. We remain in a state of denial and ignorance that climate change is not an issue to worry about. Or perhaps, when it is said that climate change has already caused intense environmental impacts, people are forced to retreat and believe that it is already too late to focus on it now.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					To sensationalize the climate change policies and its impact on the health of the people and environment leads to people believing that way. So while it may not be too late to reverse the damage, we just might leave the world for the future generation who will have to survive on borrowed time.
				&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;
					We are the last generation to fully reap the benefits of a world that didn’t have to worry about the climate, and the first generation to suffer from the consequences of the climate change that will continue to wreak havoc unless controlled and reversed.
				&lt;/p&gt;</content>
	</entry>
</feed>